Okay טוב. tov. Today's דף daf we are in the final פרק
perek of בבא בתרא Bava Batra and today's דף daf is קס"א,
kuf samech aleph, 161. We just began the פרק perek yesterday and
discussed the idea of גט get which has a generic meaning of
a שטר, shtar, that is פשוט, pashut, that is, you know, that
is like unfolded, flat, and one that is מקושר, mekushar, one that
is sort of folded and knotted. And the different ways in which
they were written, and the גמרא Gemara says that the reason for
the גט מקושר get mekushar was because for כהנים Kohanim who they
would divorce their wives in a moment of spurt of like anger
and then they would regret it because then they couldn't remarry their
wives once they were divorced. So they did, they created this גט,
get, little גט, get, well not little, whatever, the our meaning of
the word גט, get, a bill of divorce that they had to
go through the knot that would slow them down and give them
time to calm down. And then we just expanded that type of
practice to be an option for writing general שטרות shtarot once that
became a way of writing a שטר, shtar, you know, like why
somebody would opt that way, I really have no idea, maybe it
was a way to give greater weight or significance to the שטר.
shtar. Anyway, so before, and now the גמרא'ס Gemara's sort of working
through the implications of how in these שטרות, shtarot, this tied שטר,
shtar, would the עדים edim be signed and what we can sort
of, the questions we have and what we can infer from that.
But before we get to that, I don't know if this was
covered yesterday, but I want to just see the brief תוספות Tosafot
on ק"ס עמוד ב, kuf samech amud bet, who asks the obvious
question, which is if this is the reason why they made this
גט מקושר get mekushar for כהנים, Kohanim, why do we no longer
require it when a כהן Kohen divorces his wife? I've never heard
of anybody making a knotted גט get nowadays. So if you take
a look at this little תוספות Tosafot on ק"ס עמוד ב, kuf
samech amud bet, he says
the following: תקנו רבנן במקושר. Tiknu Rabbanan Bimkushar. מספקא לן בזמן הזה,
Mistapkalan bizman hazeh, we have a doubt based on this גמרא, Gemara,
says תוספות, Tosafot, nowadays, כשכהן מגרש אשתו, keshekohen megaresh ishto, when a
כהן Kohen divorces his wife, אם צריך לעשות מקושר, im tzarich la'asot
mekushar, does he have to make it this way, this knotted way?
כי מתוך התקנה משמע שאין גירש כי אם מקושר, Ki mitokh hatakkanah
mashma she'ein garesh ki im mekushar, the logic of it would be
that they required this. And if they required this to slow down
the כהנים, Kohanim, why basically logically we should require it nowadays? But
of course the subtext is, but of course we never do it
nowadays, so what's the reason? Okay, אך, ach, he says, the first
one, תקנו רבנן במקושר, Tiknu Rabbanan Bimkushar, maybe in theory the answer
is we should, but then why don't we? לפי שאין אנו בקיאין
בו בטוב נכון יותר לעשות פשוט. Lefi she'ein anu bekin bo betov
nakhon yoter la'asot pashut. Since we don't really fully understand how this
גט get was done, so even though we should be doing it,
it's better to do a straight simple גט get which we know
how it's done than trying to do this and getting it like
wrong. You know, and some of those as I mentioned, some of
the large תוספות'ים Tosafoseim on the עמוד א amud aleph in general
here are not really, you know, conceptual תוספות Tosafot in trying to
figure out like what halakhic issue it is, but trying to figure
out just the concrete specifics of what the גמרא'ס Gemara's describing. So
one answer is in theory we should be doing it, but we
don't know how, so we'll do the normal one. Okay, ורי, v'ri,
אינמי, inami, or another explanation is, והוא שכיח
יותר, v'hu shekiach yoter, אינמי לא תקנו רבנן כי אם באותו מקום.
inami lo tiknu Rabbanan ki im be'oto makom. Maybe they only required
it in that one place where כהנים Kohanim would be very rash,
and then it was maybe an option elsewhere, but it was only
required in one place. אינמי, inami, third answer, so one answer is
it's required but we don't know how to do it so we
skip so we do what we know we're going to do right.
Number two is maybe it was only required in the specific place.
אינמי, inami, third
answer, ורי היה אומר, v'ri haya omer, ורי v'ri would say, שתקנו
רבנן מקושר לא שחובה לעשות, she'tiknu Rabbanan mekushar lo shehovah la'asot, okay?
It never was a requirement. Even when they had it, it was
an option. אלא
כדי שלא יפסידו נשותיהם התקינו לעשות, ela kedei shelo yafsideu neshoteihem hitkinu
la'asot, okay? Meaning they created this as a form of a גט.
get. And then somehow, you know, כהנים, Kohanim, it's like, it's like,
you know, sometimes when people in my family are dieting, I am
told do not bring any ice cream home, do not put it
in the fridge, okay? Which is like once you know it's an
option, you'll opt for it. The כהנים Kohanim knew that they were
rash, so they would, you know, so they would, they weren't required
to do this, but once it was a form of doing it,
I don't know if that was a good analogy, but you get
the point. It's like, it's like once, you know, you know your
own strengths and weaknesses, you know, so, okay, I get that I'm
rash, I get whatever, so, you know, maybe the סופר sofer will
tell me you really should use this גט get or no, you
know. But the point is it's not a rabbinic requirement. They just
made it as a form of a גט get or form of
a normal שטר, shtar, but and that served a purpose of slowing
כהנים Kohanim down when necessary that that option was out there and
available. Okay, so that was I thought just interesting, the question about
how come, you know, we've never heard of doing it nowadays if
that's its purpose. Anyway, back to the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara
was saying that
where would they do the signatures for a גט מקושר? get mekushar?
מקושר makuasher if the signatures were in the back, so there's two
answers. One answer was רב הונא Rav Huna said
that it was בין קשר לקשר. bein kesher l'kesher.
So here I'm going to, using this very nice little thing which
actually has pictures, but I'm not going to use the pictures, I'm
just going to use it to illustrate. Okay? So if it was
basically written like this, you would write some text and you would
fold it over here. Okay? Now, by the way, I should just
say that the רשב"ם Rashbam says that this part would be blank.
You'd write here and this part would be blank and you'd fold
it and you'd be מקשר mekasher it. But תוספות Tosafot says you
would write both on the top and on the bottom and you'd
fold over. Okay, and then let's see, I guess you would sort
of be done. How would you do this? You would do it
like
like this here, like making a fan, basically.
Okay, anyway, so that's how you would do it. Okay, so you
would have writing here and maybe here and make a knot, and
then here and here make a knot, right? And that's and that's
sort of how you would do it. Okay, so where would the
signatures be? So according to רב הונא, Rav Huna, the signatures would
be like here, on the white space, you know, in the back,
right? That's where the signatures would be. But the גמרא's Gemara question
was because it understood from רב הונא Rav Huna that you would
not necessarily have to have the signatures all the way down, or
you know, somehow, I mean it's a little unclear because you're supposed
to have signatures on every knot. But anyway, but the גמרא's Gemara
question was was that according to רב הונא, Rav Huna, why couldn't
you just go ahead and if you had some signatures up here,
why couldn't you just go ahead and on side B? Because if
you're writing a normal שטר, shtar, you have the שטר shtar and
you have the signatures directly
underneath. There's nowhere to add in between the last line of the
שטר shtar and the signatures. Okay? So what now we're going to
be focusing on is: how do you get it so that you
can't add information, change things after the שטר shtar has been signed?
Alright, so the גמרא's, Gemara so the גמרא's Gemara sort of in
a normal שטר shtar we would get it, you have the text
and then the signatures. But if the signatures would be on the
back, what would be to stop you on this side from going
ahead and adding stuff, like afterwards, on the bottom? So the גמרא
Gemara says you because you had the words הכל שריר וקיים, hakol
sharir v'kayam, which is what we know, that's what we have, which
basically is saying like, 'here's the end of the document, nothing can
be added after this text,' is basically what the words הכל שריר
וקיים hakol sharir v'kayam are saying. So then the גמרא Gemara says,
well maybe you wrote הכל שריר וקיים hakol sharir v'kayam twice? No,
no, no, once you write it once, you can't write it again,
that ends the document. Well, says the גמרא, Gemara, what's to sort
of stop you from erasing that and adding your text and writing
it again? So basically said, no, like erasures after a certain point
would not would not be acceptable because you would exactly be concerned
that that would happen. So that was one sort of answer, that
you can't add on this side because of הכל שריר וקיים hakol
sharir v'kayam and the you know prevents further addition,
and erasures even if you indicate the erasures don't work towards the
end of the document. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara is going to
deal with the other approach, which is that you wouldn't sort of
write it in the folds, but that you would write it along
the back, like what's כנגד הכתב. k'neged haktav. So כנגד הכתב k'neged
haktav
understood to be like if this were sort of like
this was side A, this was the כתב, ktav, and let's say
the כתב ktav stopped here, then on side B
of it, I understand that the signatures would run parallel to the
כתב ktav on side B. So according to that, you don't have
a question of how come you can't add more, right? Because the
signatures are lined up right with the end of the writing, so
obviously there wouldn't be a problem about adding more. Okay, but you
could always forge signatures, in other words add information or even... yeah,
but I could also have new signatures. Yeah, but I could also...
so the גמרא's Gemara going to ask that question, but by the
way, the simple answer is that I could always just forge a
document and forge signatures, right? So the fact that, so if I
need new signatures, might as well just actually forge the document, right?
The presumption is you're not going to forge
signatures. But that's the point, right? When we were dealing with it
like this way and it wasn't clearly corresponding to the writing, we
needed to say that there was הכל שריר וקיים hakol sharir v'kayam
that prevents further addition. Here we're going to start with assuming you
don't need הכל שריר וקיים hakol sharir v'kayam because the last signature
corresponds to the last line. Okay, that's where we're going to pick
off. Okay, your point that you could add signatures, at least on
the face of it, is not such an issue, because then why
not just, if you're forging, might as well just forge signatures, might
as well just forge a whole new document? Or even forge, I
mean actually somebody adds some text and they have more signatures. And
they... but they don't forge, they just, they didn't... yeah, but you
wouldn't sign something if the, if you're the beneficiary of the document,
if you're the מלווה, malveh, you're saying that you lent a million
dollars to Charlie, I'm not going to sign it without Charlie being
there. But your point still is a good one because once the
basic document is written, there's already signatures, maybe I can just convince
people to add their signatures already, you know, afterward. Look, it's already
good, just I'm just like, so we're going to actually get to
that. So let's look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this. ורבי ירמיה בר אבא, U'Rebbi Yirmeya bar Abba,
and according to רבי ירמיה בר אבא, Rebbi Yirmeya bar Abba, three
lines from the top on קס"א, Kuf Samech Aleph, according to רבי
ירמיה בר אבא, Rebbi Yirmeya bar Abba, דאמר אחורי הכתב וכנגד הכתב
מבחוץ, d'amar achorei haktav u'kineged haktav mibachutz, on the outside, meaning on
side B, and it's parallel to the writing on side A, ליחוש
דלמא כתיב מגואי מאי דבעי, leichosh dilma kativ miguai mai d'ba'ei, so
it's exactly here what David asked: why don't we say that you
can write on the inside what you want, ומחתים סהדי יתרי מלבר,
u'machtim sahadei yiteiri milvar, and just get extra signatures? So now the
question is, you know, what type of question is it? Like I
just said to David, heck, if you're forging anyway, I mean if
you can get people to sign what you want, let me just
get a check that said David is giving me a million dollars
and I'll get somebody to sign, you know, this or whatever, you
know, to sign it. So תוספות Tosafot says, I think תוספות Tosafot
here, תוספות Tosafot says or somebody here
says that...
wait, where be...
yes, if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, well let's... ואמר, v'amar, let's
read one more line in the גמרא Gemara and then we'll see
תוספות. Tosafot. ואמר, v'amar, and the guy will say, אנא לרווחא בעדים
הוא דעבדי. ana l'ravcha b'eidim hu d'avdi. Oh yeah, you know why
I signed extra? Oh don't you say I had enough? Like you're
supposed to only have three. I mean, here I would have it
was five. Okay, but look, you know, why did... okay, you're only
allowed three sign... you're... the standard is three. He said yeah, but
I wanted extra. So I had a few extra sign. Okay, that's
all very nice why you had extra sign, but how are you
going to convince those guys to sign, right, if the other party
isn't around? So look at תוספות, Tosafot, okay. תוספות Tosafot says, אנא
לרווחא דעדים הוא דעבדי, ana l'ravcha d'eidim hu d'avdi, וקיים בשלושה שלמעלה,
v'kayeim b'shlosha she'lemala, ואי הני תלתא מקיימי. v'ee hanei tlata mikaymei. תוספות's
Tosafot first answer is that maybe I forged those extra signatures, but
ההלכה ha'halacha is that by a שטר מקושר shtar mekushar that has...
that needs three signatures, you can just be מקיים mekayeim three of
them, you don't have to be מקיים mekayeim all of them. So
that's one answer, right? If it was getting just forging a document
from the beginning and forging the signatures, I would have to get
those signatures validated, and that's not... I'm not going to be able
to if I'm forging it, I mean unless I'm a good forger.
But if I already had three and I'm just adding some extra
lines here and adding signatures here, I can get away with forging
these signatures, right, because I can just get these, which are good
ones, validated and these ones not validated. Is that clear? Yeah, how
that'll work? You look uncertain, Eli. Yeah, I was missed yesterday. Oh
okay, you're catching up. Okay, but there are three signatures required by
a שטר גט מקושר. shtar get mekushar. Okay, and
so this would be a legitimate שטר. shtar. These are genuine signatures.
After the שטר, shtar, afterwards it's done, I'll just add... so this
basically here says, okay,
that Charlie owes Dov a thousand dollars, okay.
And then here, after we get it signed, okay, I... and Charlie
goes away, I add the word 'every month'.
Or something like that, okay.
And then I just add an extra signature there. So I can
do that, says תוספות. Tosafot. Now of course I'm... I'm forging that
signature, okay, but I can do that because I'll just get those
three מקויים mekuyam and I don't need to get the last one
מקויים. mekuyam. So why are we not afraid that I'm going to
do this? Okay. So it says, anyway, so that's one answer, okay.
Other explanation about how I might be able to get עדים eidim
to sign after I've done it, but we'll go with that with
תוספות. Tosafot. All right.
Now תוספות... Tosafot... now we go on like this.
Okay, so it says like this. אנא לרווחא דעדים הוא דעבדי. ana
l'ravcha d'eidim hu d'avdi. Yeah, I got four signatures, I wanted that
extra signatures, okay, and I'll make it look like it was all
part of the original document. אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said
back, מי סברת עדים כסדרן חתמי? mi savrat eidim kesidran chatmi? עדים
מלמטה למעלה חתמי. eidim milmata lemala chatmi. What makes you think that
they signed the normal order? They sign from the bottom up. Now
what does this mean from the bottom up? So תוספות Tosafot and
the רשב"ם Rashbam say based on the ירושלמי Yerushalmi that what it
means is that they sign like this,
they sign lengthwise, okay. So if they're signing
lengthwise...
whatever, I guess let me do it this way.
ראובן בן יעקב, Reuven ben Yaakov, okay. You know, whatever. שית בן
אדם. Shit ben Adam. Okay, whatever it is. That's how they're signing.
So then I can't add something here. This is כנגד הכתב kineged
haktav and this clearly is an added line. Okay, so if they're
starting from the bottom and going up, there's no way you could
add anything. Okay, that's... we'll go with that explanation. But by the
way, רבינו גרשום Rebbeinu Gershom sounds like it says no, it just
means from the bottom up, but as... as opposed to doing ראובן
בן יעקב Reuven ben Yaakov and then you do the next עד
eid and the next עד, eid, you start on the last line.
But of course what difference does that make? So what? So the
first guy did it this and then the next guy did it
here, you still can add one more below it. So it sounds
like no, the reason is because you don't... what? You left spaces
at the top. Yeah,
but the idea is you were going to... it may be that
allows... but the point is, oh you mean like you started at
the very bottom of a document? No, you started in the middle
and you leave spaces at the top and you see that... yeah,
but that doesn't... but you could still go one more line. So
what the answer seems to be is that you would not do
one line per עד, eid, but what you would do is you
would do something like this. You would do ראובן בן יעקב עד,
Reuven ben Yaakov eid, you know, you know ששת בן
בן אדם Shes ben ben Adam
like עד eid like that. So you know would like the the
lines would like be interwoven like there would you know be interwoven.
So in that type of a case, if you would have a
whole line here, since it would start and end on the same
line, but it would it would be clearly like you know added.
But that's not such a good explanation because then you could go
from the top to the bottom that way, you know if you
demand. Anyway, the easier explanation so we're not going to worry about
that that we're going to sort of interpret it like this way
which explains it very nicely, that if you're doing it this like
like this, there's no way you can add something afterwards. Okay, so
that's the answer. מי שחץ עדים כשרים וחתומין דלאו איני מלמטה למעלה
חתומין. Mi shechat eidim kesherim v'chatumin d'lav eini milmata l'mala chatumin. ולחוש
דלמא מיסרמי ירעותא בשיטה אחרונה, V'leichosh dilma misramia reiusa b'shita achrona, the
last line says something bad that hurts me. וגייז ליה לשיטה אחרונה
V'gayiz lei l'shita achrona and I cut off the last line. וגייז
ליה לראובן דהדא V'gayiz lei l'Reuven d'hada and cut off the word
ראובן Reuven on the other side. ומשתכח בן יעקב עד. U'mishtakach ben
Yaakov eid. So if you've got here it's saying
ראובן בן יעקב עד, Reuven ben Yaakov eid, okay, why don't I
say you know
these two lines here it says Charlie owes me $1000, but somewhere
in like these this line here it says something like this: You
know but he has paid you know already $500.
Okay, he borrowed 1000 but he's already paid 500. So I don't
like that part of the document, okay? So what I'm going to
do is so forget adding sometimes it'll help me to take away.
I will just cut the document like that, okay,
and here if it's written like this, right? If it's here like
so yeah was
ראובן בן יעקב עד. Reuven ben Yaakov eid. So now it'll still
be okay, okay? Now it has to work out perfectly that like
it makes sense that there's an end of a sentence there or
whatever and that it exactly corresponds. But anyway I cut it that
way and it just says בן יעקב עד, ben Yaakov eid, and
maybe that's a good signature, you don't need a full name, the
son of Jacob עד, eid, right? So what's going to prevent me
from doing that? Okay, so let's read that inside. ולחוש
דלמא מיסרמי ירעותא בשיטה אחרונה, V'leichosh dilma misramia reiusa b'shita achrona, the
last line says something bad that hurts me. וגייז ליה לשיטה אחרונה
V'gayiz lei l'shita achrona and I cut off the last line. וגייז
ליה לראובן דהדא V'gayiz lei l'Reuven d'hada and cut off the word
ראובן Reuven on the other
side. ומשתכח בן יעקב עד. U'mishtakach ben Yaakov eid. דתנן בן איש
פלוני עד כשר. D'tenan ben ish ploni eid kasher. Even if you
just say בן איש פלוני עד, ben ish ploni eid, that's legitimate.
Okay, so what's to prevent me from doing that? So it says
דכתיב ראובן בן בחד דרא ויעקב עד עלווי עלווי. D'chtiv Reuven ben
b'chada dara v'Yaakov eid ilavei ilavei. So you have ראובן בן Reuven
ben written in one place and יעקב עד Yaakov eid in the
other. Now what does that mean? It's all one line here. Okay,
so what it could mean is, I mean this is all very
unclear, like I said a lot of the discussions here are just
to make sense. So it could mean that the words ראובן בן
Reuven ben have to correspond to one line of text, which is
very hard, right, if you think about it. If this is going
this way and this is going this way, for two words, ראובן
בן, Reuven ben, to correspond to the height of one line, I
mean I even wrote this as two lines, but of one line
you know of text is does not it doesn't work so well.
It's possible that what it means is that you write like this:
ראובן בן
יעקב
עד Reuven ben Yaakov eid like like that. So even if, right,
you were to cut even if this corresponded to two lines of
text, you can't cut away ראובן Reuven without cutting away the בן.
ben. Okay, so therefore there's no concern you'll cut that away because
then you're just left with יעקב עד Yaakov eid which is not
enough. You at least need so-and-so the son of so-and-so, it's assuming
a first name alone does not work. You either need a full
name ראובן בן יעקב Reuven ben Yaakov or you need a last
name בן יעקב, ben Yaakov, but you can't just have a first
name. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says why are we not afraid you'll
cut it off because and be left with בן יעקב? ben Yaakov?
Because you write ראובן בן Reuven ben together so that can't work.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
יעקב עד עלווי. Yaakov eid ilavei. ולחוש דלמא גייז ליה לראובן בן
ומשתכח ביעקב עד. V'leichosh dilma gayiz lei l'Reuven ben u'mishtakach b'Yaakov eid.
But the גמרא Gemara says so what, יעקב עד Yaakov eid should
work. דתנן, D'tenan, we taught in the משנה, Mishna, איש פלוני עד
כשר, ish ploni eid kasher, that you just can say איש פלוני
עד. ish ploni eid. Yes, first names do work. So we're back
to the same problem. דלא כתב עד. D'lo katav ed. You don't
write the word עד. Ed. You just write ראובן בן יעקב. Reuven
ben Yaakov. So תוספות Tosafot says what? Like you mean to tell
me we would say if you don't have the word עד Ed
it's a more kosher document than if you do have the word
עד? Ed? Right? We tell people don't write the word עד, Ed,
just write ראובן בן יעקב. Reuven ben Yaakov. So again, like that's
what I said, some of these large תוספותים Tosafotim are just to
figure out what the heck is going on here. But anyway, that's
what it sounds like, that the practice we have been doing is
write them together and write it without the עד Ed to prevent
this type of cutting off. The גמרא Gemara is going to come
up with a better answer, so let's keep on going. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it eima, and if
you want I could say, דכתבי, D'khatvei, thank you, דאיתידע ביה דהא
חתימת ידא, D'ityada beih d'ha khatimat yada,
but we know that this signature
לאו דיעקב הוא lav d'Yaakov hu isn't Yaakov. We can tell the
signature is Reuven's. So if it said בן יעקב עד, ben Yaakov
ed, then that would be kosher because Reuven is בן יעקב. ben
Yaakov. But if he's writing it like this, and we cut it
off, and you're just left with יעקב עד, Yaakov Ed, there's no
problem that we'll be misled and thinking that's good because we know
that's not Yaakov's signature. Of course again, the question is, so I
still don't understand, you would only allow people to sign שטרות shtarot
if not only did they do this, which is okay, that could
just be a convention, you put the בן ben underneath your name,
but only if we recognize their signatures, like, going in? Or maybe
what it's sort of saying is, is that if we have to
do קיום שטרות, kiyum shtarot, maybe it's not we don't recognize the
signatures going in, but if we have to do קיום שטרות, kiyum
shtarot, the signature of יעקב עד Yaakov Ed doesn't look like a
Yaakov, it's going to look like Reuven's signature. So there won't be
a problem that this שטר shtar will be, you know, will be
sort of validated because the signature here is going to be not
the signature of any Yaakov, it'll be the signature of Reuven. All
right, so still, like again, you see these large תוספותים, Tosafotim, still
not exactly clear, but that seems to point the point. But the
גמרא Gemara says like this: ודילמא בשמיה דאבוה חתים? V'dilma bishmei d'avuh
khatim? Okay, but even יעקב עד, Yaakov Ed, even without the word
בן, ben, maybe that's just the signature he uses. He uses his
father's name, but it's Reuven's signature. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
no: לא שביק איניש שמיה דידיה וחתים בשמיה דאבוה. Lo shevik inish
shmei dideih v'khatim bishmei d'avuh. People don't have basically the חוצפה chutzpah
to just use their father's name. They might write בן יעקב עד,
ben Yaakov ed, they're not going to use their father's name. So
the גמרא Gemara says: ודילמא סימנא בעלמא הוא דשוייה? V'dilma simana b'alma
hu d'shavyeih? Maybe it's not using it as a name, maybe it's
sort of using it as a symbol, like as a family, you
know, sort of like an insignia that they, and we're going to
see people would sign sometimes with like a crest or a symbol,
so maybe he's not calling himself יעקב, Yaakov, it's more sort of
like symbolizing like the family. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, which again is a little funny going
from a picture that's a symbol to a name that's a symbol,
but okay. So the גמרא Gemara says דשוייה
דהא רב צייר כוורא. d'shavyeih d'ha Rav tzyar kavra. Rav would draw
a fish to be his like symbol of instead of signing his
signature. ורבי חנינא צייר חרותא. V'Rabbi Chanina tzyar charuta. Rabbi Chanina would
draw a palm tree. ורב חסדא סמך. V'Rav Chisda Samekh. Rav Chisda
would just write the letter סמך Samekh for חסדא, Chisda, I guess.
ורב הושעיה עין. V'Rav Hoshaiah Ayin. ורבא בר רב הונא מקותא. V'Rabba
bar Rav Huna makuta. Rabba bar Rav Huna would draw like a
mast of a ship. So therefore maybe they're just using the name
as a symbol and not actually their name or a father's name.
לא,
לא חציף איניש ושוי לשמיה דאבוה סימנא. Lo, lo khatzif inish v'shavi
l'shmei d'avuh simana. Same reason you're not going to sign with your
father's name, you're not going to use your father's name just as
a type of a symbol for your signature. Okay, so basically even
though you in theory could cut it off, we're not afraid because
יעקב עד Yaakov Ed will there's it's not Yaakov's signature, it's your
signature, and we're not afraid. All right, so that was like one
whole set of answers. Yes, now the גמרא Gemara is going to
give another answer. Yep. Using a fish, that was a Christian symbol
even by the time he was alive. Okay, I don't know if
the Christians had fully appropriated that that nobody else could use that
symbol. Anyway, he's in בבל, Bavel, right? There were Christians there. Yeah,
what was Rav was early, third century? Yeah, the fish was used
by the second century. It was an acronym for the Greek word
for fish is actually an acronym for a Christian theological statement. Interesting.
Okay. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: מר
זוטרא אמר למה לך כולי האי? Mar Zutra amar lama lakh kulei
hai? Why do you have to give all those answers? Those are
pretty bad answers. So he says no: מקושר שאין ידיו כלין בשיטה
אחת פסול. Mekushar she'ein yadav kalin b'shita akhat pasul. No,
the answer is is that if they don't all end on the
same line, it's invalid. Now what the heck does that mean? Okay,
they all ended on the same line. Still the question is why
don't you just cut it off? So the what it sounds like
from the רשב"ם Rashbam and רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom is it sounds
like, and this would have been such an obvious answer that you
really understand why didn't you just say this going in, that if
we basically like right and left justify everything, okay, or bottom and
top justify everything. Right, ראובן בן יעקב עד, Reuven ben Yaakov ed,
you know whatever, אדם, Adam, no, wait, and שת בן אדם. Shet
ben Adam. We spread it out and we justify everything, okay? Who
else should we do?
יצחק בן אברהם. Yitzchak ben Avraham. Okay, עד. ed. So if we
justify everything and names are going to be different sizes and they're
going to be different spread out, the basic point is when you
cut off, you have to go, you have to cut off everything.
So these things are going to, so it's clearly going to be
a cut because maybe you can get one thing to be exactly
aligned with the line, but this will be half a word in
and this will be, you know, two-thirds of a word in and
this will be a word and a half in. So you'll basically
see, meaning apparently what it thought was, maybe what it initially thought
was you were doing something like this: you were doing like, I
don't know, ראובן בן יעקב עד, Reuven ben Yaakov ed, and then
here you would do, I don't know, you would insert it maybe,
you know, שמעון, Shimon, you know, בן ben whatever, and you know,
here אדם Adam or whatever, so you could cut off like that,
maybe is what it thought. It's hard to know what the הוה
אמינא hava amina was. But the answer is if everything is aligned,
its starting point is aligned, and you do a cut, the cut
is not going to go, is not, is going to cut through
some words even though it might be aligned with one of the
words. Okay, so that was an easy enough answer, you wonder why
we didn't say that going in. Anyway, all right. Oh, we are
finally done with that, which was very technical and figuring out exactly
where the signatures were and how to prevent it. But the upshot
of it is that the גמרא Gemara is concerned, the consistent point
about all of this is that the גמרא Gemara is concerned with
how do you prevent after a document has been signed, changes to
be made afterwards? And one of the things we basically said was
that if you make changes, first of all you have the in
the version that we were doing the signatures were in the fold,
okay? We said you have the word הכל שריר וקיים. Hakol sharir
vekayam. Reason for this is because it's assuming you don't have הכל
שריר וקיים. Hakol sharir vekayam. So we'll get to that in a
minute. But some documents presumably had it, some didn't. הכל שריר וקיים
Hakol sharir vekayam would basically be a way of saying you cannot
add anything beyond this point. And then the only question was how
do you prevent like erasures and you have to validate erasures, etc.
If you don't have הכל שריר וקיים, Hakol sharir vekayam, it's more
complicated. How do you indicate that the document is over? But that
is the concern of the גמרא. Gemara. How do you prevent things
from being added afterwards? הכל שריר וקיים Hakol sharir vekayam is a
simple answer, but not all documents had it. And how do you
prevent erasures and corrections? And the answer is you need to validate
those at the end of the document. Yes, Charlie. Nowhere in here
are they discussing what the documents are on, is it pap? Right,
that's discussed elsewhere, which is a good point because a document had
to be on a type of a thing that if you would
make an erasure, the erasure would be visible, okay, in exactly for
this, and with a type of an ink that the erasure would
be visible because otherwise you would just be able to forge it
and people wouldn't even know that any erasure had occurred. So you
are correct, that's discussed elsewhere. Okay, so now with that in mind,
now we gotta just talk more broadly about the way שטרות shtaros
are written without and their requirements without like this technical question of
how the folds are and where the signatures are. So let's read
a little bit further. אמר רבי יצחק בר יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן:
Amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Yosef amar Rabbi Yochanan: כל המחקים כולם צריך
שיכתוב ודין קיומיהון. Kol hamichakim kulam tzarich sheyichtov v'den kiyumeihon.
Okay,
so now we're dealing with this issue about, okay, but you have
to sometimes make corrections. So how do you make corrections? So he
says: okay, you make the corrections, you erase, and then at the
bottom you say, here were the corrections that I made. Now the
question is, there's a question whether you have the word ודין. v'den.
These are. Meaning the question is, do you have to introduce it
with the phrase at the
end? Right? You say basically, דמנא דכשר
למקניא ביה, d'mana d'kashar l'mikanya bei, right? And then we would normally
say הכל שריר וקיים. Hakol sharir vekayam. Okay, but before, which basically
says, that's it, end of document. Okay, and we discussed earlier like
how do you prevent הכל שריר וקיים Hakol sharir vekayam from being
erased and put things, putting things afterwards? Because you only accept erasures,
right?
After you have this, you know, no erasures beyond this point, that's
what we said yesterday. So since there are no erasures allowed after
that point and you write הכל שריר וקיים, Hakol sharir vekayam, you
can't do anything. You can't erase that and add more and write
it because no erasures are allowed after that point. But what you
can also do beyond this post, after this point, is write, before
הכל שריר וקיים, Hakol sharir vekayam, you could write, you could write
something like, you know, what's it say, what's it say here? ודין
קיומיהון. V'den kiyumeihon. Right? So the words would be something like,
you know, we, I think let me see if the רשב"ם Rashbam
has the exact language. Hold on.
What? Hold on, let me see the language of the רשב"ם. Rashbam.
ודין והפירוש כל המחקים שנמצאו במקום שהרי קיומם דאמינו להלן דצריכים לקיימם
צריך לקיימם בסוף שטרא לפני שחותמין שמן ומשו לא לגבי שטר ולכתוב
בסוף... V'den v'haperush kol hamichakim shenimtza'u b'makom she-harei kiyumam d'aminu lehalan d'tzrichim
lekaymam tzarich lekaymam b'sof shtara lifnei she-chotmin shimun v'mashu lo l'gaybei shtar
v'likhtov be-sof...
No, it doesn't exactly have the language. Okay, yeah, I mean he
doesn't have it exactly either, but you would basically say, let me
see if תוספות, Tosafos, he might have had it before.
Hold on.
Okay, yeah, I mean he doesn't have it exactly either, but you
would basically say something like, you know, that so-and-so ודן קיומיהון, ve'den
kumeihon, you know, these are this is the sort of corrections that
we made, although קיומיהון kumeihon doesn't exactly mean corrections, and then you
would sort of like list. We, you know, this word was erased
in the second line, you know, בשורה ב beshura beis we erased,
you know, there was a מחק, machak, you know, whatever, then בשורה
ג beshura gimel and you would sort of list the corrections. Okay,
now some so that's if you said that you have to say
ודן קיומיהון, ve'den kumeihon, these are the corrections colon. Other versions do
not have the word ודן קיומיהון, ve'den kumeihon, it says צריך למכתב
קיומיהון. tzarich lemichtav kumeihon. So you just meaning you don't have to
write v quote these are the corrections and then list them, you
just it means it's saying at the end you have to write
what the corrections are. Okay, and that's sort of what תוספות Tosafos
says is our is our approach and the רשב"ם. Rashbam. We do
not have a phrase here are the corrections. Okay, we just say
them. So he says you say וקנינא מן מנא דכשרנא ומקניא ביה,
ve'kanina min mana de'kashrana u'makanina bei, you know, and then before we
say הכל שריר וקיים hakol sharir ve'kayam we say, you know, בשורה
שניה, beshura shniya, you know, מחק, machak, whatever, you know, בשורה, beshura,
you know, ג, gimel, you know, ארבע arba we have a word
is תלויה, tluya, we have a word that was suspended, and you
basically write any corrections, and then you write הכל שריר וקיים. hakol
sharir ve'kayam. Okay, so that's how we deal with that. So you're
so and and since you're not allowed any erasures and הכל שריר
וקיים hakol sharir ve'kayam ends it, you know that that is going
to be right that that you can't fake anything after that point.
Okay, so let's read that again. אמר רב יוחנן כל מחקים כולם
צריך שיכתוב ודן קיומיהון או צריך שיכתוב קיומיהון. amar rav yochanan kol
machakim kulam tzarich she'yichtov ve'den kumeihon o tzarich she'yichtov kumeihon. We'll read
it that way. You have to you have to indicate you have
to be מקיים mekayem them, but you מקיים mekayem them by noting
them at the end of the שטר. shtar. וצריך שיחזור מעניינו של
שטר בשיטה אחרונה. ve'tzarich she'yachzor me'inyano shel shtar beshita achrona. And so
that's point number one. Point number two is is that you have
to repeat now this assumes that you did not say הכל שריר
וקיים, hakol sharir ve'kayam, okay? And what it says is, here's ראובן
בן יעקב עד, reuven ben yaakov ed, okay,
יצחק בן אברהם עד, yitzchak ben avraham ed, I know, okay, there,
whatever, they're uncles they're uncle and nephew they're not allowed to sign.
Anyway, so it says you the last line has to be has
to repeat the the discussion of the שטר. shtar. Now what does
this mean? So the simple sense of this means that you have
to have some type of a recap at the end, okay?
And the problem with that is is that there are so the
problem with saying that you need a recap is that some שטרות
shtaros like do not have a recap.
If you take a look actually actually first of all I wrote
it wrong because I wrote this over here, but according to the
רשב"ם Rashbam the
צריך שיחזור מעניינו של שטר tzarich she'yachzor me'inyano shel shtar is מעניינו
של שטר בשיטה אחרונה me'inyano shel shtar beshita achrona this is the
last line is וקנינא מן ve'kanina min so and so אל מן,
al min, you know, ר מן remin whatever, שמשון Shimshon על כל
מה דכתיב ומפורש לעיל. al kol ma de'chtiv u'meforash le'eil.
We get a קנין kinyan on everything that was written. Okay, that's
חוזר על עניינו של שטר. chozer al inyano shel shtar. You don't
actually rewrite the whole שטר shtar how you supposed to rewrite the
whole שטר shtar on the last line but you refer to the
whole שטר, shtar, okay? We were קונה koneh from him on everything
that was discussed above ומנא דכשרנא למקניא ביה. u'mana de'kashrana le'makanaya bei.
Okay,
and you have to do that in the last line. Now why
do you have to do that in the last line? So the
reason is because
when these guys sign, okay, they are not going to sign directly
up against the text. They're going to leave a little bit of
a space. All right, now if they're going to leave a little
bit of a space, there's a concern that maybe they leave a
little bit of a space and somebody's going to come in and
write in something else here, right? Like I said, Charlie owes me
a thousand dollars and here I wrote every month. Okay? So because
I am sort of like sum it all up, okay, so there's
one way sort of saying like that's a way to basically say
that like that you know that there's nothing to be added after
this point. I've summarized everything. And more than that, since the point
is that the last line is just supposed to summarize, what that
really leads- Is the next הלכה *halakha*, which is אין למידים משיטה
אחרונה *ein lamedim mishitah achronah*. The only thing the last line is
supposed to do is to summarize and therefore we're going actually make
a rule that no
legal meaning of the שטר shtar. *shtar* can be derived from anything
written in the last line. The last line, it's basically we're saying
the last line is only supposed to be boilerplate and if it's
not, we ignore it. Okay, that's the basic point. So therefore and
the reason we ignore the last line is to prevent somebody sneaking
in a line there. So here you write the last line, so
you make it boilerplate because you don't want to add something important
even if nobody sneaks anything in, we want to make sure there's
nothing that is here that is more than boilerplate, okay, and if
somebody sneaks something in and adds something concrete it'll be ignored. Okay,
does the last line have to be the top line or is
it on the very bottom? No, the last line before the עדים
*edim*. So why what would hold you back from sneaking something in
that you wouldn't include in this total summary, I mean, because... Well
where I don't understand where would you? Between the upper line and
the עדים *edim*, and then on top of the עדים *edim* you
put in... Okay, here's the שטר *shtar*, right? Let's number the lines,
okay, let's say it's a גט *get*, a גט *get* has 12
lines,
okay,
and then it's the, על כל מה דכתוב ומפורש *al kol ma
d'chtiv u'meforash*. So that was just boilerplate, it says on everything, and
then we have יעקב *Yaakov* whatever בן *ben* whatever עד *ed* etc.
Okay, so this is boilerplate, so don't put anything important here. If
somebody sneaks something in here, it'll be ignored anyway. The thing that
might be that might be adjacent to the יעקב *Yaakov* further down
and you might have space between that. I could see a five-line...
And you have a big space here? Yeah, so... Right, so the
assumption is is that you would not give a lot of white
space. Move it back up? Right, I mean, yeah, you'd make sure
the עדים *edim* would be close to the text so that you
can't don't wouldn't give a lot, right, if you gave a lot
of white space then somebody could write two lines, one
of
substance and then a boilerplate line afterwards, you'd be in trouble. But
don't leave all that white space, okay? But you've got to leave
some white space to give them a little space to sign. Okay,
so וצריך דמעניינו של שטר בשיטה אחרונה *v'tzarich d'mei'inyano shel shtar b'shitah
achronah*. מאי טעמא *Mai ta'ama*? What's the reason? אמר רב עמרם *Amar
Rav Amram* לפי שאין למידים משיטה אחרונה *lefi she'ein lamedim mishitah achronah*,
in order since because we're going to rule that there's no you
can't learn from the last line in order to prevent people from
sneaking in something substantive. Therefore we're going to tell you that just
summarize the שטר *shtar* and don't do anything else. Now here there's
an interesting discussion in one of these long תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* in
discussion. Does that mean that the last line, like I'm saying, just
should be boilerplate, which is what the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* says? It's
really just advice like hey, don't say anything new in the last
line because we're not going to learn from it. Okay, or is
it saying no, there's really a requirement in the last line to
say some type of a summary line. Let's say I didn't say
anything new in the last line, right? I just sort of said
yada yada yada. Whatever, I said like דלא כאסמכתא ודלא כטופסי דשטרי
*d'lo k'asmachta u'd'lo k'tofsei d'shtarei*.
Okay,
that's not a חוזר על עניינו של שטר inyano shel shtar, *chozer
al inyano shel shtar*. I'm not saying I'm not referring to the
whole שטר *shtar* to the things, but it's but it's also just
boilerplate. So the רשב"ם *Rashbam* says that's all we really mean, just
mean it's just telling you don't say anything of substance in the
last line. But תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* has a whole discussion because other
גמרות *Gemarot* sound like there's a requirement to say something summarizing in
that last line. So that's how to interpret that requirement of עניינו
של שטר *inyano shel shtar*. But basically they agree that the point
is to not allow there to be something of substance sneaked in
afterwards. Now, אמר ליה רב נחמן *Amar lei Rav Nachman*, let's just
read a little more. אמר ליה רב נחמן לרב עמרם מנא לך
הא *Amar lei Rav Nachman l'Rav Amram mana lach ha*, where do
you get this idea from? Where was this רב עמרם *Rav Amram*?
Oh, who said אין למידים *ein lamedim*? אמר ליה דתניא *Amar lei
d'tanya*. הרחיק את העדים שני שיטין מן הכתב פסול *Hirchik et ha'edim
shnei shitin min hakatav pasul*. There you go, Eli. If you give
two white lines after the end of the document, it's פסול *pasul*
because you're giving a person a chance to sneak in an extra
line. שיטה אחת כשר *Shitah achat kasher*, one it's okay. מאי שנא
שני שיטין *Mai shena shnei shitin*? דלמא מזייף וכתב *Dilma mezayef v'chatav*.
Two lines, no, because you're giving a guy an option to put
in something in that white space. שיטה אחת נמי מזייף וכתב *Shitah
achat nami mezayef v'chatav*? So one line he's always giving him an
option? אלא לאו שמע מינה אין למידים משיטה אחרונה שמע מינה *Ela
lav shema mina ein lamedim mishitah achronah shema mina*. You don't learn.
Okay, now, so we now look at look how the דפים *dapim*
are so small, so we're already half a דף *daf* ahead. So
let's just look briefly at this very large תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*, but
it's one of the few תוספותים *Tosafotim* here that's discussing a sort
of a ruling rather than a technicality. לפי שאין למידים *Lefi she'ein
lamedim*, look at this תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*. בימיהם לא היה כתוב שריר
וקיים sharir v'kayam, *B'yameihem lo haya katuv sharir v'kayam*. Now, that's what
I sort of said a minute ago, right? We saw from the
earlier discussion in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* that often שריר sharir, וקיים
*sharir v'kayam* wasn't there because the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is always concerned
you'll add something in at the end. So תוספות *Tosafot* says this
whole issue of a concern for white space is because you don't
write שריר וקיים *sharir v'kayam*. But if you would just write the
words שריר וקיים, you wouldn't have to worry about white space afterwards;
you've basically already said nothing can be added beyond this point. All
right. So he said ובפשיטון שלהן, U'v'pishitan shelahen, in their simple, their
non-מקושר. mekushar. כדאמר גבי מקושר לעיל דכתבי שריר וקיים. K'd'amar gabi mekushar
l'ail d'katvei sharir v'kayam. מכלל דבפשיטין לא יכתבו שריר וקיים. Miklul d'v'pishitin
lo yichtevu sharir v'kayam.
It sounds like that was the exception, the rule would be you
wouldn't write it. ומכך לא ילמדו משיטה אחרונה. Umikach lo yilmedu m'shita
achrona. שלא יוכלו להזדייף בשיטה אחת שירחיקו העדים ויכתבו חזרת השטר בשיטה
אחרונה. Shelo yuchlu l'hizdayeif b'shita achas she'yarchiku ha'edim v'yichtevu chazaras hashtar b'shita
achrona.
They would just write some summary because since there was no שריר
וקיים, to prevent anything substantive being added. ולא שום דבר עיקר שאין
ללמדים הימנו. V'lo shum davar ikkar she'ein l'lamdim heimenu. ואם אירע בהן
מחק, V'im eira bahen machak, and let's say there was an erasure,
היה כותב אותו והיו מקיימים אותו קודם שיטה אחרונה, Haya koteiv oso
v'hayu m'kaymim oso kodem shita achrona, right?
So that's why here, I put the again because the רשב"ם says
the word וקנינא v'kanina is the עניינו של שטר, so the קיום
המחק kiyum hamachak
would be before that. So that obviously would be substantive. And then
you would write the sort of the boilerplate last line.
Where were we? Okay. והיו מקיימים אותו קודם שיטה אחרונה. V'hayu m'kaymim
oso kodem shita achrona. דאחרי כן לא ילמדו כל עיקר
הימנו, D'acharei chen lo yilmedu kol ikkar heimenu, because afterwards, after that
last line, could not have anything of substance that was necessary for
the שטר. ויש לתמוה. V'yeish litmoha. So that's what it sounds like
from the גמרא. Gemara Now we should be astounded. איך הורגלנו לכתוב
קיום מחקים אחר וקנינא מיניה? Eich hurgalnu lichtov kiyum machakim achar v'kanina
minei?
Which is how I first wrote it and I corrected it because
our practice is exactly the reverse. You write וקנינא מיניה v'kanina minei
and then you do the קיום מחקים. kiyum machakim. So he says,
"How do we do that?" That's exactly clearly not what was going
on in the גמרא. Gemara? Okay. דהא אין למדים משיטה אחרונה ואין
לך למדים גדול מזה. D'ha ein lamdim m'shita achrona v'ein l'cha lamdim
gadol mizeh.
There's nothing more of substance than actually validate corrections. גדול מזה ראוי
לנו לומר לפי שהיה יכול לבוא לידי זיוף כיון דשטר כשר בלא
שריר וקיים שפעמים לא יכתוב מתחילה שריר וקיים ויעבור זה וימחוק מה
שירצה ויגיה ויקיים המחק בסוף ויכתוב שריר וקיים. Gadol mizeh ra'ui lanu
lomar lefi she'haya yachol lavo lidei ziyuf keivan d'shtar kasher b'lo sharir
v'kayam she'p'amim lo yichtov mitichila sharir v'kayam v'ya'avor zeh v'yimchok mah she'yirtzeh
v'yagiyah v'ykayeim hamachak b'sof v'yichtov sharir v'kayam. Okay.
He says that if we allow non-שריר, right? So then basically, if
we do the וקנינא v'kanina and then the קיום מחקים, kiyum machakim,
so he says what you could basically do is you could write
that, you do the קיום, kiyum, anyway, you could, he says, now
that he says you can basically just, you know, forge it and
get away with it since we do this, we don't have a
boilerplate last line. Our last line actually is something of substance. ויש
לומר. V'yeish lomar. The answer is כיון שהורגלנו לכתוב שריר וקיים והיה
פסול אם לא נכתב כן אפילו כשאין בו מחק והשתא לא יוכל
לבוא לידי זיוף וכך אנו כותבין שפיר קיום מחקים אחר וקנינא מיניה
ולמדים אנו בשיטה אחרונה כיון שאנו כותבין שריר וקיים. Keivan she'hurgalnu lichtov
sharir v'kayam v'haya pasul im lo nichtav ken afilu k'she'ein bo machak
v'hashta lo yuchal lavo lidei ziyuf v'kach anu kotvin shapir kiyum machakim
achar v'kanina minei v'lamdim anu b'shita achrona keivan she'anu kotvin sharir v'kayam.
Okay. So תוספות basically says, his answer is, is that this is
the way the גמרא Gemara had it, this last thing was boilerplate
and you couldn't learn from it. So it says our practice is
we do the וקנינא v'kanina up
here, okay, וקנינא מיניה v'kanina minei etc. So what about the problem
about you can't learn from the last line because of a concern
that things will be added afterwards? So תוספות says no problem, we
just write הכל שריר וקיים. Hakol sharir v'kayam. And then once we
write that, okay, we're able to learn from the last line because
the whole problem was we were afraid somebody was going to sneak
something in. But this basically prevents somebody from sneaking something in. Okay?
So once we are in a document with הכל שריר וקיים, Hakol
sharir v'kayam, all these concerns that you're going to add to it
go away. And once those concerns go away, we're able to go
ahead and learn right up through to the last line. Okay? And
that's why we can do the קיום מחקים kiyum machakim there. So
then תוספות basically says, then he goes through and says, well, how
come we're doing it different from the time of the גמרא? And
he goes through a whole thing trying to figure out why our
practice changed. Okay. But anyway, but this is how we get, in
the time of the גמרא it was clear that they did not
end a lot of documents with הכל שריר וקיים, Hakol sharir v'kayam,
so it was all these concerns about cutting off and adding, and
you have to need the last line has to be boilerplate, you
can't add anything. And in the end, תוספות says, but what we
actually do is our last line is not boilerplate, it is substantive,
but we end with הכל שריר וקיים Hakol sharir v'kayam and that
prevents anything from being added after the end of the document. Okay?
So we will end with this and